<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-03-03T07:59:18+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pindi Krishna Chandra Prasad</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What Are The Defining Characteristics of The Learning Sciences?</title><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2022/Characteristics-LS/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Are The Defining Characteristics of The Learning Sciences?" /><published>2022-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2022/Characteristics-LS</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2022/Characteristics-LS/"><![CDATA[<p>The following essay was written for a graduate psychology class I took at LMU Munich. It is based on the description of the Learning Sciences programs provided in the article by <a href="https://eprints.nottingham.ac.uk/52659/1/Sommerhoff%20et%20al%20%282018%29%20What%20do%20we%20teach.pdf" target="_blank">Sommerhoff et al. (2018)</a>, and comments on how I would locate the Learning Science program offered at LMU Munich in respect to the spectrum of the programs offered by other institutions. (The word limit was ~ 500 words.)</p>

<hr />

<h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>The learning sciences investigate learning and teaching, do related theory-building and method development, and work to transfer their insights into practice (Fischer, 2018). The present essay provides an overview of these activities, first covering the learning sciences’ defining characteristics and how academic programs train learning scientists. Next, design-based research (DBR)’s and learning analytics’ merits and shortcomings are discussed, as they are among learning sciences’ signature methods (Fischer, 2018). In closing, applications of learning sciences’ scaffolding and multimedia principles are reviewed. Concluding remarks are provided in the final section.</p>

<h2>Characteristics</h2>
<p>The learning sciences first emerged about 30 years ago (Kolodner, 2004). The field has since grown, with researchers from psychology, educational sciences, computer science, philosophy, and others joining forces to inquire and enhance learning and teaching. Hence, one defining characteristic is the learning sciences’ interdisciplinarity, rooted in the conviction that this will lead to a more holistic understanding of learning (Fischer et al., 2018).</p>

<p>The learning sciences are viewed as a community of practice due to their collaboration, mutual engagement, common goal, and shared set of concepts and methods (Sommerhoff et al., 2018). Notably, the learning sciences do application-oriented research, i.e., empirical work of practical use and embedded in real-world contexts (Fischer et al., 2018). This differentiates them from similar fields such as cognitive science, which tend to deprioritize socio-contextual factors (Hoadley, 2018). Learning scientists also use various qualitative and quantitative tools in their inquiry, with different approaches and use cases for each, which fits the broad research matter of learning and teaching. Empiricism lies at the core of these methods (Hoadley, 2018).</p>

<p>Whether the learning sciences are its own discipline remains debated (Hoadley, 2018). Arguably, an acknowledged research discipline would be granted a university department (Chandler, 2009). However, to my knowledge, no learning sciences departments currently exist within higher education. Learning sciences’ only formal space is related scientific journals (e.g., the Journal of the Learning Sciences) and academic conferences (e.g., the ISLS Annual Meeting). However, there are now several learning sciences master’s and Ph.D. programs.</p>

<h2>Learning Sciences Programs</h2>
<p>How future learning scientists are trained at academic institutions paints a picture of current methodological and conceptual foci. Sommerhoff et al. (2018) report that most graduate programs in the learning sciences prioritize DBR and “traditional statistics” in their methods curriculum. They also show a conceptual focus on technology-supported learning, cognition, learning in informal contexts (e.g., museums), and learning design.
LMU Munich’s program favors frequentist statistics, traditional psychological research methods, and psychometrics (i.e., 24 out of 120 ECTS) but includes no courses on DBR. This is an interesting deviation, as Sommerhoff et al. (2018) report DBR is covered in 1 out of 2 psychology-affiliated learning sciences programs. At the same time, the LMU program’s conceptual content is mainly aligned with the study’s other programs, as it centers around technology-supported learning (P1.2 and WP4), cognition (P1.1 and WP3), and domain-specific learning (WP1-6). Interestingly, there are no learning design courses but others on organizational learning and meta-level topics (e.g., educational systems), which few to none of the programs in the study report. Notably, both the master’s thesis project and internship allow LMU students to pick their topics. These two modules make up one-third of the program’s ECTS, leaving much of the methodological and conceptual focus up to students’ choice.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Academic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following essay was written for a graduate psychology class I took at LMU Munich. It is based on the description of the Learning Sciences programs provided in the article by Sommerhoff et al. (2018), and comments on how I would locate the Learning Science program offered at LMU Munich in respect to the spectrum of the programs offered by other institutions. (The word limit was ~ 500 words.)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Scientific Reasoning and Causal Learning</title><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2022/Scientific-Reasoning-and-Causal-Learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scientific Reasoning and Causal Learning" /><published>2022-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2022/Scientific%20Reasoning%20and%20Causal%20Learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2022/Scientific-Reasoning-and-Causal-Learning/"><![CDATA[<p>The following essay was written for a graduate cognitive development class I took at LMU Munich. The task was to articulate a problem statement considering developmental processes that impact on teaching and learning and to critically discuss the stated problem along two relevant theories from developmental research using empirical findings. (The character limit was ~14 000 characters.)</p>

<hr />

<h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>Scientific reasoning (SR) is defined as the abilities and cognitive processes required to use the scientific method (Díaz et al., 2021). SR helps us understand connections between actions and outcomes in daily life (Kuhn, 2012), enables evidence-based decisions in our professions (Berndt et al., 2021), and enhances students’ understanding of science subjects (Kuhn, 2011). Well-developed SR is characterized by the systematic, intentional obtainment of relevant information and knowledge, complemented by reflective abilities (Morris et al., 2012).</p>

<p>Research on SR focuses on the three domain-general abilities of hypothesis generation, investigation and experimentation, and evidence evaluation (Zimmerman &amp; Klahr, 2018). Albeit studies report indications of SR abilities in children, adolescents and adults often fail on SR tasks (e.g., Kuhn, 2007, 2012). For example, they misconstrue or dismiss contradictory evidence, engage in unsystematic and uninformative experimentation, and seek confirmatory evidence for their prior beliefs (see Zimmerman &amp; Klahr, 2018).</p>

<p>The literature contains two explanatory accounts for this seeming contradiction. The first stems from the literature describing the development of scientific reasoning (DSR). It argues that findings exaggerate young children’s SR abilities, highlighting that corresponding tasks’ demands are considerably lowered, nevertheless leading to children making errors in exploration, experimentation, and evidence evaluation (e.g., Kuhn, 2011). It also notes that children tend to favor effect-producing strategies over informative interventions (i.e., the “Positive Testing Strategy”; Shtulman &amp; Walker, 2020), which indicates a lack of systematicity, intentionality, and metaconceptual understanding. The second explanatory account derives from the causal learning literature. Building on ample research, it maintains that “children’s learning mechanisms do indeed resemble the basic inductive processes of science” (Gopnik, 2012, p. 1624), and posits that previous studies have misinterpreted adolescents’ and adults’ valid inquiry and evidence evaluation strategies in SR tasks as uninformative and false (Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2021).</p>

<p>The present essay first summarizes the two accounts’ interpretations of children’s hypothesis generation, investigation and experimentation, and evidence evaluation. In conjunction, their core claims regarding the SR failures of adolescents and adults are reviewed, and implications for education are derived. After that, the accounts are compared and discussed in their explanatory power for the seeming contradiction in the literature. In closing, limitations and future directions are outlined.</p>

<h2>DSR Literature</h2>
<p>The DSR literature notes that children often struggle to differentiate between theories, hypotheses, and evidence, cling to false prior beliefs in the face of contradictory evidence, and overlook confounding variables when determining causal effects (e.g., Kuhn, 2011; Schauble et al., 1991; Tschirgi, 1980; Zimmerman &amp; Klahr, 2018). Moreover, to engage in SR tasks, children require lowered task demands and guiding constraints that are unrepresentative of the real world (e.g., forced-choice paradigms with just one causal variable; Kuhn, 2012; Zimmerman &amp; Klahr, 2018). Leaning on these results, DSR scholars posit that children show shortcomings in their investigation, experimentation, and evidence evaluation in SR tasks (e.g., Kuhn, 2012). Notably, evidence around children’s hypothesis generation skills is still scarce. One study by Piekny and Maehler (2013) reported that preschoolers show difficulties completing related tasks, possibly due to overwhelming metacognitive requirements.</p>

<p>For the cases where children succeed on rudimentary SR tasks, DSR scholars stress that they do so without the intentionality, systematicity, and meta-cognitive skills characteristic of well-developed SR (e.g., Kuhn, 2012). For example, Tschirgi (1980) and Schauble et al. (1991) concluded from their studies that children prefer to produce interesting outcomes over deconstructing cause-and-effect relationships. This points toward children lacking an explicit understanding of what makes a good experiment and effective strategies for obtaining informative evidence. Notably, only few empirical studies on DSR have explicitly targeted metacognitive awareness and intentionality in SR tasks. Among them, interestingly, is contradictory new evidence by Köksal-Tuncer and Sodian (2018) and Köksal et al. (2021): They found preschool-aged children can differentiate between uninformative and informative evidence, judge their own knowledge states (e.g., ignorance or lack of evidence to make a claim), and provide verbal disconfirmation when presented with false causal claims.</p>

<p>The broader claim by the DSR literature remains that children and adults primarily differ in their metacognitive abilities to adequately assess and use evidence to revise false prior beliefs and differentiate between theory and evidence (Zimmerman &amp; Klahr, 2018). Albeit it is acknowledged that adults usually have well developed metacognitive abilities, they still often go on to fail on SR tasks (e.g., Kuhn, 2007). The DSR literature explains that adult SR tasks often build on prior knowledge and entail more complex causal structures (e.g., multiple potential causal variables and interactions). If adults’ prior knowledge and beliefs conflict with the evidence in the task, they have to reconcile the two – a difficult task that requires prior skill-building (Kuhn, 2012). It follows that we should neither expect untrained adults to perform well on SR tasks nor children to become adults with well-developed SR without training and instruction (Shtulman &amp; Walker, 2020).</p>

<p>Hence, schools need to devote attention to the explicit training of SR abilities and related metacognitive skills. For one, they can implement question-asking practices in their classrooms, such as encouraging students to ask “why?” and “what if?” questions. This can help them identify what they do not yet know, support their explanations, and build a habit of considering alternative hypotheses (Shtulman &amp; Walker, 2020).</p>

<h2>Causal Learning Literature</h2>
<p>The causal learning literature has termed children “little scientists” not only due to their intuitive theories about the world (e.g., intuitive physics), but because their “learning mechanisms do indeed resemble the basic inductive processes of science” (Gopnik, 2012, p. 1624). Starting in preschool age, they can design interventions to learn about causal structures, systematically test hypotheses, engage in more exploration if evidence is confounded, choose informative interventions over uninformative ones, and learn from these processes to revise their hypotheses and theories (Köksal-Tuncer &amp; Sodian, 2018; Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2020; McCormack et al., 2016; L. E. Schulz &amp; Bonawitz, 2007). The causal learning literature interprets these findings as evidence of children’s investigation, experimentation, and evidence evaluation skills being akin to those of scientists (Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2021).</p>

<p>Notably, children’s use of evidence and SR strategies alone is insufficient to infer intentionality and conceptual understanding (Köksal-Tuncer &amp; Sodian, 2018). Some recent causal learning studies on exploratory play indicate that children are aware of different types of evidence to some extent. For example, they actively isolate potential causal variables when evidence is ambiguous (Cook et al., 2011). However, research explicitly targeting metacognitive awareness and conceptual understanding is thin spread.</p>

<p>Notably, the causal learning literature documents a trend of children’s SR abilities steadily increasing with age: “Even the youngest children tested appear to grasp already the fundamental concepts and skills of scientific inquiry and inference, and this is followed by steady, incremental progress towards consistently correct performance with increasing age.” (Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2021, p. 4). This is backed by recent longitudinal studies showing that albeit SR performance does not improve linearly, older children generally do show growth in their SR abilities (e.g., in experimentation and evidence evaluation; Lazonder et al., 2021; Piekny &amp; Maehler, 2013).</p>

<p>Lapidow and Walker (2021) posit that especially adults’ attempts at SR tasks may have been misinterpreted as false and irrational despite being valid. In their “interventionist theory of causal learning,” causal knowledge entails knowing if throwing a stone (X) into a window causes it to break (Y). In contrast to the DSR literature’s disapproval of PTS, Lapidow and Walker argue that PTS is a valid choice for determining causality: Collecting data on one instance where X is absent cannot determine with certainty what happens if X is in play. In contrast, repeatedly testing what happens if X is present can – it addresses the question of whether the outcome (a broken window) invariantly occurs when the cause (throwing a stone into the window) is in play. Therefore, children’s and adults’ preference for PTS should not be seen as an erroneous, uninformative strategy but “as a rational and informative approach to generating evidence” (Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2021, p. 7). Hence, the authors note that evidence found for children’s and adults’ failures on SR tasks may well be less severe than the DSR literature argues.</p>

<p>As for implications for education, the causal learning literature notes that children learn considerably from their exploration and play. Thus, schools and early childhood education should refrain from structuring and formalizing their environments to mirror formal educational contexts (Gopnik, 2012). Instead, they should maintain room for children to learn informally, e.g., through pretend play. While explicit instruction is not advisable, educators and caretakers can, for instance provide scientific explanations related to everyday events or carefully introduce children to counterintuitive information and ask them to explain their intuitions (Gopnik, 2012).</p>

<h2>Comparison of Accounts</h2>
<p>For three reasons, I conclude that the causal learning literature has more been consistent with recent findings and provides a more convincing explanatory account. First, there is now ample evidence of children’s abilities around investigation, experimentation, and evidence evaluation in SR (e.g., Köksal-Tuncer &amp; Sodian, 2018; Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2020; McCormack et al., 2016; Schulz &amp; Bonawitz, 2007). The DSR literature traditionally argued that children are fundamentally deficient in these areas but has come to concede that children do at least show certain SR precursors (e.g., Shtulman &amp; Walker, 2020). The documented trend indicates that children’s SR abilities develop with increasing age, underlined by longitudinal studies (Lazonder et al., 2021; Piekny &amp; Maehler, 2013), aligning with the causal learning literature’s claims (e.g., Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2021).
Relatedly, the DSR literature argues that children and adults differ fundamentally in their metacognitive abilities to revise their beliefs and differentiate hypotheses and evidence (e.g., Zimmerman &amp; Klahr, 2018). However, new research now finds that young children can indeed distinguish between hypotheses, theories, and evidence (e.g., Köksal-Tuncer &amp; Sodian, 2018a). Despite adults allegedly being more well-developed metacognitively, they still often fail on SR tasks (Kuhn, 2007; Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2021). The DSR literature has argued that the average adult lacks the explicit training and education to navigate researchers’ demanding SR tasks (Shtulman &amp; Walker, 2020), but the underlying prediction was nevertheless rendered false.</p>

<p>Lastly, the DSR literature has stressed that children often engage in SR tasks with a “Positive Testing Strategy” (PTS; Shtulman &amp; Walker, 2020). A considerable part of this claim rests on early studies (e.g., Schauble et al., 1991; Tschirgi, 1980) that remain widely cited in current theoretical work and reviews (Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2021; Zimmerman &amp; Klahr, 2018). However, recent findings from Lapidow and Walker (2020) indicate that their preference for desirable outcomes does not primarily drive children. Moreover, Lapidow and Walker (2021) have posited a theoretical account explaining how PTS can be considered an effective and informative hypothesis testing approach instead of an erroneous one.</p>

<h2>Limitations and Conclusion</h2>
<p>Scientific reasoning (SR) entails the abilities and cognitive processes required to use the scientific method, specifically hypothesis generation, investigation and experimentation, and evidence evaluation (Díaz et al., 2021). Literature around SR has reported that young children engage in SR similar to scientists, but that adolescents and adults often fail on SR tasks (e.g., Zimmerman &amp; Klahr, 2018).</p>

<p>The causal learning literature has provided a convincing explanatory account for this seeming contradiction through its extensive documentation of children’s early SR abilities (e.g., Gopnik, 2012), first reports of children’s awareness and systematicity in SR (e.g., Cook et al., 2011; Schulz &amp; Bonawitz, 2007), the supported prediction of continuous SR development (e.g., Lazonder et al., 2021; Piekny &amp; Maehler, 2013), and a novel theoretical account identifying PTS as an informative and valid approach to SR (Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2021).</p>

<p>It should be noted that drawing a sharp distinction between the causal learning and DSR literature may no longer be appropriate: Recent longitudinal studies and works that aim to tackle the gaps around metacognitive skills of children (e.g., Köksal-Tuncer &amp; Sodian, 2018a; Lapidow &amp; Walker, 2020; Lazonder et al., 2021) effectively build on both literature strands, and widely cited scholars such as Schulz produce findings in cognitive development as well as causal learning (e.g., Schulz, 2012; Schulz &amp; Bonawitz, 2007). A different framework for comparing opposing accounts in the literature should be considered for future reviews.</p>

<p>Ultimately, scholars from both strands have contributed much to our understanding of children’s development in SR and the mechanisms of their exploratory play. First educational policy suggestions for nurturing these aspects have been made (e.g., Gopnik, 2012). If early childhood education and schools build on these findings, society will benefit from more citizens well-versed in SR, for example, holding a better understanding of science subjects (Kuhn, 2011), and making better evidence-based decisions in their professions (e.g., Berndt et al., 2021).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Academic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following essay was written for a graduate cognitive development class I took at LMU Munich. The task was to articulate a problem statement considering developmental processes that impact on teaching and learning and to critically discuss the stated problem along two relevant theories from developmental research using empirical findings. (The character limit was ~14 000 characters.)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Virtual Reality and Empathy</title><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2022/VR-and-Autism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual Reality and Empathy" /><published>2022-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-01T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2022/VR-and-Autism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2022/VR-and-Autism/"><![CDATA[<p>The following essay was written for a graduate neurocognitive psychology class I took at LMU Munich. The task was to present a phenomenon/empirical finding that is relevant to brain plasticity, discussing two empirical papers in detail. (The character limit was ~14 000 characters.)</p>

<hr />

<h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>Immersive virtual reality (IVR) places the user into a computer-generated but vivid scenario rich with sensory input, eliciting a strong sense of immersion and creating the illusion of a real experience (Suh &amp; Prophet, 2018). IVR also prompts strong, “realistic” psychological and physiological user responses (e.g., emotions; Diemer et al., 2015).</p>

<p>IVR is accessed either by using an HMD (Head-Mounted Display) or CAVE (Cave Automatic Virtual Environment). The HMD is a headset with two integrated lenses the user puts on. CAVE projects the IVR content onto multiple screens that physically surround the user. Both of them track the user’s head movements, among other things, continuously updating what is displayed to match the user’s viewing perspective as they move. Gonzalez-Franco and Lanier (2017) argue this aligns IVR content with what the user’s brain expects to happen next, so they “tend to treat the simulated reality as real, which in turn will engage additional neural mechanisms to further the veracity of the illusion” (p. 2).
The hypothesized supporting neural mechanisms are threefold (Gonzalez-Franco &amp; Lanier, 2017): sensory input from multiple modalities is congruent and can thus be integrated well (bottom-up multisensory processing), the user feels the motor actions they take in IVR are indeed initiated by them (sensorimotor self-awareness), and the user can take actions in IVR to confirm predicted outcomes (top-down prediction manipulation). However, whether VR indeed elicits the same brain response as a real experience remains controversial. Related empirical findings are still scarce, as established neuroimaging methods conflict with the modalities of IVR (Bailenson, 2018): The user’s ability to move their body to navigate the virtual space is key to IVR but causes issues for EEG (e.g., increased noise due to movement artifacts) and fMRI (subjects are required to lie still).</p>

<p>Hence, applied studies focusing on IVR’s practical implications for brain plasticity – the human brain’s remarkable ability to adapt its structure and connections in response to stimuli and changing demands (Kolb &amp; Gibb, 2011) – are more numerous. For example, IVR is used successfully in treating deficits in clinical populations (e.g., treatment of phobias; Rizzo &amp; Koenig, 2017) and enhancing abilities in regular populations (e.g., learning and teaching in schools; Hew &amp; Cheung, 2010). Notably, one of the technology’s core advantages is access to realistic experiences without the risks of the real-life scenario. This has proven especially useful for training social skills in people with ASD as it enables them to practice social interaction flexibly and repeatedly without embarrassment or trouble (Ip et al., 2018). Similarly, IVR is also useful for training empathy and prosocial behavior in adults (Herrera et al., 2018): it creates a vivid illusion of reality where the user can embody any object or living being, including people allowing you to embody someone else’s perspective. Hence, the present essay reviews two related pieces of evidence: a study by Ip et al. (2018) using IVR to enhance social and emotional skills in children with ASD, and a study by Herrera et al. (2018) using IVR to improve adults’ empathy and perspective-taking abilities.</p>

<h2>Study A</h2>
<p>Although controversial, the research literature broadly describes people with ASD as having “deficits in emotional and social adaptation skills” (Ip et al., 2018, p. 1). To help children with ASD better integrate into society, Ip et al. (2018) ran an IVR intervention program with 94 primary school students from Hong Kong, targeting said emotional and social adaptation skills. It is the largest study conducted in this strand of research thus far (see Bailey et al., 2021; Mosher et al., 2021 for extensive reviews).</p>

<p>The study employed an experimental design where the treatment group (N = 47) went through the IVR intervention, accompanied by a trainer, whereas the control group (N = 47) did not receive the intervention. Children in the treatment group completed a pre-assessment phase, an intervention phase, and a post-assessment phase. Children in the control group only completed the pre- and post-assessment phases. The authors hypothesized that the intervention group children would show significant improvement on all post-assessment measures of emotional and social adaptation skills, while control group children would show no significant improvement.</p>

<p>In the pre- and post-assessment phases, all children (and in some cases their parents) completed questionnaires and tests regarding their cognitive profile, emotion recognition, emotion expression, emotion regulation, and social adaptive skills. In the intervention phase, the children completed 28 IVR training sessions over 14 weeks. The authors designed six IVR scenarios that broadly matched the daily experience of Hong Kong schoolchildren. For instance, in scenario three, the user is in the school library and handles various social challenges like sharing their workspace with others and borrowing a book at the library counter (Ip et al., 2018). All scenarios were presented in half-CAVE, i.e., the IVR content was projected onto a setup with four screens surrounding the user.</p>

<p>In summary, the study reported most of the expected positive effects: By the end of the 14 weeks, the intervention group children had significantly improved on measures of emotion expression, emotion regulation, and social reciprocity. However, they showed no improvement in their emotion recognition or social adaptive skills. Interestingly, while control group children showed no pre-post differences on most measures, they improved on two social skills subscales, i.e., communication and community use (e.g., road crossing behavior). Unfortunately, the authors do not mention if the control group children could participate in other interventions or training parallel to the study. Since the study spanned five months, and all children in the sample were “required to attend mainstream school in the inclusive education setting,” (Ip et al., 2018, p. 1) it is possible control group children underwent training in road crossing behavior, leading to the observed improvements.</p>

<p>The study aligns with the rest of the recent empirical evidence (see Mosher et al., 2021) in indicating that IVR interventions can help children with ASD build social skills in an engaging and effective way. However, the study contained disproportionately few girls, i.e., just 8 out of 94 participants. Future studies should recruit a much higher proportion of girls so that the results’ interpretability is not limited to boys. The study’s replicability is also limited and made difficult both for researchers and practitioners interested in (re-)testing the intervention: not only is the IVR setup highly specific (i.e., complicated hardware and IVR content tailored toward Hong Kong schoolchildren), but it is also expensive according to the authors.</p>

<h2>Study B</h2>
<p>Herrera et al. (2018) designed and conducted two separate studies, of which only the first is reviewed in the present essay. They investigated how an IVR perspective-taking task affects empathy and prosocial behavior compared to a traditional perspective-taking task, both short- and long-term. The target population to empathize with were the homeless because they are “considered an extreme outgroup that people often struggle to empathize with … [and] anyone can become homeless.” (p. 6)</p>

<p>One group completed a traditional narrative-based perspective-taking task (NPT; N = 56) and the other a perspective-taking task in IVR (VRPT; N = 61). The authors hypothesized that compared to NPT participants, VRPT participants would show increased empathy and prosocial behaviors both right after the intervention and in the long term within eight weeks after the intervention. In the NPT, participants imagined becoming homeless and then read a narrative text. In the VRPT, participants experienced homelessness in IVR. The narrative shown in IVR matched the narrative in the NPT’s text, containing three scenes: 1) eviction out of your own apartment, 2) living out of your car leading to a police encounter, and 3) seeking shelter on a bus with the worry of getting your things stolen.</p>

<p>The study contained a pre-intervention phase, an intervention phase, a post-intervention phase, and a follow-up phase. In the pre-intervention phase, participants answered demographic questions and completed two scales, one assessing differences in empathy and the other assessing beliefs about empathy. Next, participants completed either the NPT or the VRPT in about 15 minutes. In the post-intervention phase, right after task completion, all participants completed a range of self-report scales and questionnaires on empathic concern, personal distress, closeness and connectedness to homeless people, dehumanization of homeless people, and attitude toward homeless people. Participants were also asked about their agreement with “proposition A” concerning affordable housing, their willingness to sign a related petition, and what amount they are willing to donate to homeless shelters. In the follow-up phase, participants completed further prosocial behavior tasks (writing letters about the homeless and stating how much they agree with “measure B” regarding affordable housing).</p>

<p>In summary, the VRPT intervention showed some positive short-term effects (increased empathy and personal distress) and long-term effects (improved attitude toward the homeless and less dehumanization) compared to NPT. However, other measures such as closeness and connectedness with, dehumanization of, and attitudes toward the homeless saw no change. As for prosocial behavior, while the amount donated to homeless shelters and the support for a “proposition A” did not differ across conditions, VRPT participants gave significantly more signatures on the petition supporting affordable housing.</p>

<p>There are a few criticisms to be raised. First, among the many measures the authors administered, they did not include a measure of social desirability. This is surprising – the study design lends itself to influences of social desirability, and valid short-form measures (e.g., “Marlowe-Crowne Social Desirability Scale”; Fischer &amp; Fick, 1993) are readily available. Second, the authors argue IVR avoids the biases and preexisting schemas of participants since the task scenario “is all rendered digitally, and […] at an advantage in terms of accurate content, in comparison to traditional perspective-taking” (p. 4). However, this argument ignores that the programming of IVR content is also done by humans with biases and schemas. Thus, researchers should not assume it is inherently bias-free. On a positive note, study B provided detailed descriptions of its IVR setup and narrative, even making the used IVR content freely downloadable in the Steam Store (https://store.steampowered.com/app/738100/Becoming_Homeless_A_Human_Experience/). This is a great example of easing replicability for researchers and practitioners.</p>

<h2>Discussion and Conclusion</h2>
<p>Ip et al. (2018) and Herrera et al. (2018) have provided evidence for IVR’s potential in enhancing adults’ empathy and perspective-taking abilities and building the social and emotional skills of children with ASD. Both studies succeeded in helping individuals build skills essential to integration into society, human interaction, and society’s functioning as a whole. They also jointly demonstrate two major strengths of IVR-based interventions: For one, IVR can mimic scenes from real life in an authentic, engaging, and safe way. This is of practical use to children with ASD so that they can practice social interaction flexibly, repeatedly, and without embarrassment. It also allows anyone to dive into scenarios that are otherwise associated with considerable real-life risks, such as the experience of homelessness. Second, IVR comes with high control over the content shown to the user, which is advantageous to both interventions and experimental studies as it ensures standardization and replicability.</p>

<p>As for brain plasticity, neither of the reviewed studies employed neuroimaging methods. Still, they add to the applied research literature in discussing IVR’s potential for treating deficits in clinical populations and enhancing abilities in regular populations. Albeit ASD is considered a developmental disorder with persistent symptoms and deficits (Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 2013), Ip et al.’s work (2018) adds to the evidence (see Bailey et al., 2021; Mosher et al., 2021) that these aspects are not immutable but can be improved so that the individual can better deal with society’s demands. Herrera et al.’s (2018) work also highlights IVR’s ability to make users perceive a simulated experience as real, although outcomes were mixed. Whether this illusion of a real experience can be explained by the neural mechanisms Gonzalez-Franco and Lanier (2017) propose – i.e., bottom-up multisensory processing, sensorimotor self-awareness, and top-down prediction manipulation – requires more neuroscientific study and advances in VR-conducive imaging methods.</p>

<p>Despite these promising findings and the many potential use cases of IVR, it should be noted that corresponding research is still in its infancy – even recent reviews note the general effects of IVR use on development are largely unknown (Bailey &amp; Bailenson, 2017; Common Sense Media, 2018). While VR manufacturers seem to acknowledge this limitation, age recommendations still vary strongly, ranging from “age seven and up, with adult supervision” to “should not be used by children under age 13” (Common Sense Media, 2018). It is thus essential that both the VR industry and scientists continue treading with caution in how and with whom they employ IVR. Bailenson (2018, p. 322) puts it succinctly: “[…] if an experience is not impossible, dangerous, expensive, or counterproductive, then you should seriously consider using a different medium—or even doing it in the real world. Save VR for the special moments.”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Academic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following essay was written for a graduate neurocognitive psychology class I took at LMU Munich. The task was to present a phenomenon/empirical finding that is relevant to brain plasticity, discussing two empirical papers in detail. (The character limit was ~14 000 characters.)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Objections to Subjectivity and the Subject of Objectivity:Is Psychology a Natural Science or a Social Science?</title><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/psychology-natural-or-social-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Objections to Subjectivity and the Subject of Objectivity:Is Psychology a Natural Science or a Social Science?" /><published>2021-03-08T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-08T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/psychology-natural-or-social-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/psychology-natural-or-social-science/"><![CDATA[<p>I had written the following text as a graded essay for a philosophy class I took during my time at HU Berlin, thus the rather formal structure and content. Disclaimer: I do not think I was able to answer the leading question of this essay sufficiently, as it undoubtedly is a very difficult one. Anyway, as always, here goes.</p>

<hr />

<h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>The field of psychology first emerged as a branch of philosophy, and it continued to remain so until the middle of the 19th century (cf. <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/9781118133880.hop201003" target="_blank">Fuchs &amp; Evans, 2013</a>, pp. 4–5). Psychology has since drastically gained in importance as the scientific discipline that inquires human behaviour and thought, and yet, institutions and scholars are not in agreement on whether and how psychology should be categorized as a scientific discipline. Such can be seen on how some universities lead their institute of psychology under the umbrella of the natural sciences (e.g., <a href="https://www.psychology.hu-berlin.de/en/portal-page?set_language=en" target="_blank">HU Berlin</a>), while others lead it under the faculty of philosophy and humanities (e.g., <a href="https://www.psychology.uzh.ch/en.html" target="_blank">University of Zurich</a>). In the following essay, I argue that while the discipline of psychology as a whole should be categorized as a social science, its subfields such as experimental psychology, cognitive neuroscience and clinical psychology should be judged independently. Key arguments of select scholars on what broadly defines the natural and social sciences and in what way psychology fits either of the two are discussed.</p>

<h2>History, Present, and Future</h2>
<p>In his letter to Raumer dated back to 1816, Hegel wrote: “The concrete [universal] divides into natural philosophy, which gives only part of the whole, and the philosophy of spirit, which comprises — beyond psychology along with anthropology and the teaching of law [Recht] and duties — aesthetics and the philosophy of religion” (<a href="https://catalogue.nla.gov.au/Record/2590251" target="_blank">p. 341</a>). Since then, psychology has long emancipated itself from the philosophy of spirit, first launching with the aim of becoming an independent scientific discipline. However, this happened not without resistance, Kant being one of various well-respected scholars reluctant to accept this change in affairs:</p>

<blockquote>
An empirical psychology of mental content could not … become a proper natural science because mental events cannot be quantified (i.e., measured or weighed), and thus its data are neither capable of being described mathematically nor subject to experimental manipulation. Finally, Kant asserted, the method of observing the mind — introspection — distorts the events observed by observing them.” (<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/9781118133880.hop201003" target="_blank">Fuchs &amp; Evans, 2013</a>, p.3)
</blockquote>

<p>After Wilhelm Wundt’s opening of what is known as the first experimental psychology laboratory in 1879, psychology slowly strengthened its status as an experimental scientific discipline (<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/9781118133880.hop201003" target="_blank">Fuchs &amp; Evans</a>, 2013, p. 1). While an array of events contributed to this, I would like to mention two in particular: First of all, Wundt, among other things, focused on measuring reaction time as an indicator for the duration of mental processes, demonstrating that introspection was not the only tool fit for studying aspects of human psychology — time, no matter whether on a millisecond timescale, was accepted to be a quantifiable measure through timekeeping (“History of timekeeping devices”, in <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=History_of_timekeeping_devices&amp;oldid=1007798923" target="_blank">Wikipedia</a></em>, n.d.). Secondly, with the addition of Galton’s and Pearson’s statistical methods towards the end of the 19th century, which were explicitly created for analytical purposes such as comparing groups of individuals (<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/9781118133880.hop201003" target="_blank">Fuchs &amp; Evans</a>, 2013, pp. 10–11), Kant’s originally valid points of criticism — failure to mathematically describe, quantify and experimentally manipulate — were now negligible. Nevertheless, psychology lacking objectivity due to the observer distorting the observation proved to be a more persistent notion — in fact, until today, it is believed to be one of the key distinctions between the social and natural sciences. Accordingly, many scholars have made arguments in regard to this distinction, of which I would like to discuss two, the first being posited by Jerome Kagan:</p>

<blockquote>
Most natural scientists hold a condescending view toward social scientists whose evidence is based on human judgments, for example, judges’ ratings of the meaning of a behaviour or a verbal report. But, as noted earlier, particle physicists often rely on the consensual judgments of experts poring over the evidence produced by a linear accelerator. Thus, the nineteenth-century distinction between objectively and subjectively based evidence has become somewhat fuzzier in modern physics laboratories. Each recording device, whether a human or a machine, registers different information, and the evidence from either device often requires consensual agreement among experts to determine meaning and validity. (<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/three-cultures/B0B2BBB8B7254D189C67C0227864E1F4" target="_blank">Kagan, 2009</a>, p. 82)
</blockquote>

<p>So, even if an “objective” entity (e.g., a machine) gathers the data, any one of the steps that follow will inevitably involve human beings, since evaluated data still needs to be interpreted, for which — to my knowledge — there exists no machine yet. Needless to say, it is those same human beings doing the interpreting which inevitably come with flawed human judgment, which in turn makes up the “subjectivity” the natural sciences seek to avoid.</p>

<p>There is an important premise that needs to be pointed out here: In his essay <em>Die Logik der Sozialwissenschaften</em>, the academic and philosopher Karl Popper argues why it is misled to assume that objectivity of science relies on the objectivity of the operating scientist. In the eleventh of the text’s 27 theses, he mentions that the natural scientist is just as partial in favouring his own ideas and theories as all other human beings: Some of the most excellent contemporary physicists have founded schools of thought that are explicitly geared towards opposing any new ideas. Popper follows up with what is his twelfth thesis, where he notes that what is considered scientific objectivity lies solely in the tradition of criticism, and that it is this tradition which allows for the prevailing dogma to be criticized against all resistance. In other words, the objectivity of science is not an individual matter, but rather a matter of mutual criticism — the act of scientists distributing the work, keeping each other on their toes, ultimately working together and against each other at the same time (<a href="http://link.springer.com/10.1007/s11577-017-0425-6" target="_blank">“Die Logik der Sozialwissenschaften”</a>, 2017, p. 221).</p>

<p>However, for the sake of argument, let’s consider Popper’s claim inadmissible, and assume that objectivity of measurement is indeed only founded in the operating scientist, respectively the tool at hand — this would require for the discipline of psychology to be in possession of a tool that is the equivalent of the linear accelerator from physics, like Kagan mentions. We are in luck: Roughly two decades ago, around the turn of the millennium, the methods of neuroimaging achieved a massive breakthrough. Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) provided a novel way of capturing changes in blood flow in the brain, and so cognitive abilities could be directly observed from a perspective never seen before: Instead of having to heavily rely on surface-level phenomena such as visible emotion or physical response, there was now a refined way of gathering data on what happens beneath the surface during those same processes (“Functional magnetic resonance imaging”, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Functional_magnetic_resonance_imaging&amp;oldid=1008966690" target="_blank">in <em>Wikipedia</em></a>, n.d.). Not only did these methods prove to be useful in various disciplines like psychology and medicine, but with its biophysical basis, experts from the natural sciences — especially physicists — were now much needed in associated scientific projects and studies, leading up to much interdisciplinary collaboration.</p>

<p>Besides further blurring the line between psychology as a social science and the “higher” standards of natural sciences, this recent development underlines another point: Psychology can hardly be seen as a unified, homogenous field anymore. As an academic discipline, it encompasses a vast range of subfields, from neurocognitive psychology and psychophysics to social psychology and media psychology. As human behaviour and thought by definition is embedded in anything that involves humans, psychology as an applied practice also picks up on many facets of human society such as delinquency (criminal psychology), work (industrial and organizational psychology) and mental health (clinical psychology and psychotherapy). This begs the question: Is it even warranted to judge psychology as an entire discipline anymore?</p>

<p>On this note, I would like to go into two more scholars’ views. Professor Billman-Mahecha, a scholar of psychology, argues that “methods do not serve to unify the psychological discipline”. According to her, methodological questions seem to have become a matter of identity, holding more weight than the underlying theoretical positions and the kind of questions that are inquired in the field. In the 20th century, a divide was sparked, a tug of war between <em>natural sciences</em> and <em>humanities</em>, <em>objectivity</em> and <em>subjectivity</em>, <em>nomothetic</em> and <em>idiographic</em>, and most recently, <em>quantitative</em> and <em>qualitative</em>. She notes that while psychology has developed a few notable methods of its own such as <em>test theory</em> in psychometrics, most of them have been adopted and adapted from other fields, concluding that the further methodological development of psychology will not contribute to its unity in any way (<a href="https://www.zpid.de/pub/psychologie-und-geschichte/0935-0179.2001.9_3-4_117-127.pdf" target="_blank">Billmann-Mahecha</a>, n.d., p. 124). Thus, the answer in how the field should be categorized must lie elsewhere.</p>

<p>Fortunately, in the same text previously cited in this essay, Popper also dissolves some of this tension, providing a convincing argument as to why it makes sense to categorize psychology as a social science: Human thinking and behaviour largely depends on social context — for example, a) imitation, b) language, and c) family are all social categories, as they rely on a) another being providing a basis for imitation, b) another being being there to converse with and c) a group of beings existing for them to be able to stand in relation to each other. According to Popper, it is clear that the psychology of learning and thinking, but also psychoanalysis, would be impossible without any one of the aforementioned: For example, a readily available opposite is vastly important to learning and thinking (e.g., <a href="https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/fbff/9f3387db16ae3a5776655885c6a25ea2ffff.pdf" target="_blank">Dautenhahn &amp; Nehaniv</a>, 2007), and psychoanalysis necessitates the client expressing their thoughts in language. This means that psychology presupposes societal terms, and it logically follows that it is impossible for psychology to completely explain society and its phenomena on its own. Now, what represents the study of society are the social sciences, but as we just established, psychology cannot be seen as the fundamental science of it — the social sciences do not rely on psychology. On the other hand, however, psychology <em>does</em> depend on the social sciences: The social categories that it presupposes are founded in concepts of the social sciences, and so the social sciences must be fundamental to psychology.</p>

<p>Consequently, I propose that in universities and academia, institutes of psychology and the field as a whole should be led under the umbrella of the social sciences. In light of the vast range of psychology subfields and the ongoing methodological divide, each subfield in question should however be judged on its respective employed methods and theoretical foundations: For example, while the cognitive neurosciences — with methods such as fMRI — adhere to the principles and standards of the natural sciences, social psychology with its use of qualitative tools and strong societal orientation is more in tune with the study of the social sciences.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Both the history and present of psychology are characterized by a lack of clear belonging and unity. The field started out as a branch of philosophy and weathered the storm of criticism from scholars such as Darwin, finding ways of quantifying as well as experimentally manipulating human thought and behaviour. As it evolved into an independent experimental discipline, the standard of objectivity remained hard to live up to, but Popper’s questioning of the concept of objectivity as well as recent methodological advances in neuroimaging methods increasingly blur the line — what is left is the question of what the underlying difference between the natural and social sciences as a whole really is. While psychology ended up being a multi-faceted study encompassing many applied and theoretical branches, its foundation presupposes concepts from the social sciences, while the social sciences do not presuppose concepts from psychology. Thus, psychology can indeed be categorized as part of the social sciences, although this does not necessarily warrant categorizing all of its subfields as social sciences. Lastly, it is likely that the existing divide in the theoretical framework and methodology within the field will persist, which is something to keep in mind for further works on this matter.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="HigherEducation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I had written the following text as a graded essay for a philosophy class I took during my time at HU Berlin, thus the rather formal structure and content. Disclaimer: I do not think I was able to answer the leading question of this essay sufficiently, as it undoubtedly is a very difficult one. Anyway, as always, here goes.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stepping Into the Learning Sciences</title><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/stepping-into-the-learning-sciences/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stepping Into the Learning Sciences" /><published>2021-02-06T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-06T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/stepping-into-the-learning-sciences</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/stepping-into-the-learning-sciences/"><![CDATA[<p>Not too long ago, probably sometime around summer last year, I first came across the term “Learning Sciences”. In case you’re hearing about it for the very first time right now, what comes to mind for you? What do you envision the field to be about? Hold that thought!</p>

<p>I still remember what <em>I</em> thought back then: Just like with many other disciplines — think <a href="" target="_blank">Cognitive Neuroscience</a> or <a href="" target="_blank">Computational Sciences</a> — , the name does not feel entirely telling as to what it’s actually about. Fast forward maybe a year or so, and it just so happens that three weeks from now, I’ll be starting a research internship at <a href="" target="_blank">ETH Zurich</a>’s Professorship for Learning Sciences and Higher Education (<a href="" target="_blank">LSE</a>). I only just recently realized this odd sequence of events, and then another thought crossed my mind: Do I feel like I <em>now</em> know what the Learning Sciences are? Well, let’s put it to the test!</p>

<h2>The Background of the Learning Sciences</h2>
<p>Admittedly, I already somewhat <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priming_(psychology)" target="_blank">primed</a> you: I mentioned the words “field”, “disciplines”, “research”, “professorship”, and “education”. And you’ve <em>learned</em> things before, obviously. But what do you see before you when you think of learning? University? Music school? Online courses? Documentaries? Workshops? Driving school?</p>

<p>Let’s start with a dry definition and then go from there:</p>
<blockquote>
The learning sciences is an interdisciplinary field that studies teaching and learning. Learning scientists study a variety of settings, including not only the formal learning of school classrooms, but also the informal learning that takes place at home, on the job, and among peers. The goal of the learning sciences is to better understand the cognitive and social processes that result in the most effective learning and to use this knowledge to redesign classrooms and other learning environments so that people learn more deeply and more effectively. The sciences of learning include cognitive science, educational psychology, computer science, anthropology, sociology, information sciences, neurosciences, education, design studies, instructional design, and other fields. (<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/cambridge-handbook-of-the-learning-sciences/2E4224681267E61DBCE9B27630ED17BA" target="_blank">Cambridge Handbook of Learning Sciences</a>, p. 37)
</blockquote>

<p>Now, as we’d like to make sense of it all, I think you’d agree that textbook definitions are a rather boring and ineffective way of doing so. And we wouldn’t want to be <em>ineffective</em> in learning about effective learning, would we? So, instead, we’ll first go back in time — but not just one year, and not just ten years either. One hundred is more like it!</p>

<p>Schools at the beginning of the 20th century followed something called <em>instructionism</em>, and people had little to no idea about how humans actually learn things. If they had ideas, they were nothing more than untested hypotheses — there was no such thing as scientifically investigating various teaching styles, classroom settings or school curricula, let alone how informal learning occurs in places such as museums or libraries.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/old-classroom-480.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/old-classroom-800.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/old-classroom-1400.webp" />
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/old-classroom.jpeg" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
1920s Boarding School. Photo source: <a href="https://www.pinterest.com/pin/19492210863411834/" target="_blank">Pinterest</a>.
</div>

<p>Unfortunately, instructionism is not just a thing of the past. It is likely that you yourself have experienced it firsthand: It’s a paradigm in which there’s a person with expertise (usually a teacher) whose role it is to pass on the “things” that they are an expert in. These “things” are <em>facts</em> (truths about the world; e.g., “<a href="" target="_blank">Bern</a> is the capital of Switzerland”) and <em>problem-solving procedures</em> useful to navigating the world (e.g. multiplication and division). According to this framework, students come to school with “empty minds”. These empty minds are to be filled up with said facts and procedures, so that students can go on and perform their later jobs. The more of these facts and procedures a person knows, the more “educated” they are, and how much they know is determined by <em>testing</em> them on their knowledge. The standard curriculum starts out with the easier facts and procedures and then progresses to more complex ones as time goes on. However, what’s considered complex is always up to the experts, not the students —this means that the experts set the order, pace, and content of what is taught.</p>

<p>There is a lot to unpack here regarding why instructionism fails to properly facilitate learning in today’s world— people have written entire books on this. But one very important component is that 21st century jobs require <em>deep conceptual understanding</em>, not just plain “knowledge” of facts and procedures:</p>

<blockquote>
Educated graduates need a deep conceptual understanding of complex concepts and the ability to work with them creatively to generate new ideas, new theories, new products, and new knowledge. They need to be able to critically evaluate what they read, to be able to express themselves clearly both verbally and in writing, and to be able to understand scientific and mathematical thinking. They need to learn integrated and usable knowledge, rather than the sets of compartmentalized and decontextualized facts emphasized by instructionism. (<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/cambridge-handbook-of-the-learning-sciences/2E4224681267E61DBCE9B27630ED17BA" target="_blank">Cambridge Handbook of Learning Sciences</a>, p. 38).
</blockquote>

<p>A simple example of this, which I’m sure everyone can relate to, are formulas in mathematics. Let’s take the binomial theorem from secondary school algebra: You learn that
\((a+b)^2 = a^2+2ab+b^2\)
and exam questions will require you to apply this formula. However, in the exam, you are then asked to factor
\(z^2+k^2+2kz\)
– suddenly the order of the terms is different, the letters are too, and instead of expanding you are now factoring, i.e. “going the other way”. Knowing the <em>fact</em> of the binomial theorem and the <em>procedure</em> of expanding will not be enough, although you may have been encouraged to learn it this way — you’ll also need to understand <em>why and how</em> the theorem is to be modified to fit this novel context. And it is exactly that which requires deep conceptual understanding.</p>

<p>So, how can deep conceptual understanding be taught, or rather, facilitated? This question is not necessarily a novel one. In fact, it brings us to the second half of the 20th century.</p>

<h2>How else can learning and teaching be viewed and done?</h2>
<p>The following paragraphs will only focus on a few select figures and ideas that were important to the development of the field, more specifically to formal learning (e.g. school contexts). There are many more worth mentioning, but for now, I’d like to focus on just the concept of <em>scaffolding</em> and two researchers named Vygotsky and Piaget:</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lev_Vygotsky" target="_blank">Lev Vygotsky</a> introduced the very interesting notion of the <em>zone of proximal development</em> (ZPD). The idea behind the ZPD is that there are tasks outside of each student’s “zone” of tasks they can do fully on their own, but that those out-of-reach tasks can be reached with appropriate help. Once the student receives said help, he learns, expands his zone and advances to the next task. “By actively participating in working through these more complex tasks, children learn from the experience and go beyond what they can accomplish alone.” (<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/cambridge-handbook-of-the-learning-sciences/2E4224681267E61DBCE9B27630ED17BA" target="_blank">Cambridge Handbook of Learning Sciences</a>, p. 82)</p>

<p><em>Scaffolding</em> is another conception of supporting a person’s learning process. You could view it as giving hints or prompts that are just enough for someone to keep making progress towards a goal, but still letting them construct the necessary knowledge to eventually reach it all by themselves. An example of this is a child that can’t tell where the next puzzle piece goes: Instead of showing or telling it where to put the piece, you could instead ask a question such as: “When you look at the shape of that puzzle piece, is there any gap in the puzzle that looks similar to it?”. The child thus still has to make sense of the shape, scan the puzzle, and recognize potential matches all by itself.</p>

<p>Although this technique may seem obvious, and may even be put to use often in parenting, it is not all that common in classrooms. One reason for that may be the usual teacher-student ratio. Fortunately, scaffolding does <em>not</em> necessarily require a physical tutor for each child — it can for example also be done by adding prompts and tips to learning software or book exercises!</p>
<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/piaget-480.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/piaget-800.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/piaget-1400.webp" />
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/piaget.png" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
Jean Piaget, 1968. Photo source: <a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/67/Jean_Piaget_in_Ann_Arbor.png/220px-Jean_Piaget_in_Ann_Arbor.png" target="_blank">Wikipedia</a>.
</div>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean_Piaget" target="_blank">Jean Piaget</a> thought about how children operate, develop and make sense of the world. One of the ideas of his I especially like is that <em>new ideas always emerge from old ones</em>, also implying that children are not an empty vessel to be filled with knowledge, but rather that they come with preconceptions and ideas about the world. For example, there is much research on how <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2011/infant-cognition-0527" target="_blank">infants have an understanding of the basic rules of the physical world</a>, which is of course in direct contradiction to the hypotheses of instructionism. Piaget’s ideas also have many more implications, but instead of going into the nuances and details of all of them, I’d like to end this text by picking up on the one connected question that I feel is most important here:</p>

<h2>How can these insights be applied?</h2>
<p>First of all, if we had the definitive answer to that, you would probably already know about it, and the world would look very, very different. However, despite the academic field of learning sciences still being in its youth (it is only roughly 30 years old!), it has already produced a good amount of promising ideas which are either already in place or being tested. Here’s a few of them:</p>
<ul>
    <li>Focusing on improving instructional techniques is not enough — students have to also actively engage in their own learning. Thus, students’ learning processes should also be subject of research, and this demands the use of both quantitative and qualitative research methods</li>
    <li>Students reflecting on their developing knowledge and expressing that in some form is crucial to their learning; this can be done in spoken conversation, written form, illustration, or by creating any kind of artifact</li>
    <li>Facts and procedures are important, but the aim is to make their application to the real world and interrelatedness obvious. The <em>learning environment</em> is essential in achieving this, and <em>project-based learning</em> leverages exactly that: Groups of students start with an unsolved question or problem, share and discuss ideas, draw from scientific practices and apply them to the matter, utilize the technologies available for hints when stuck (scaffolding), share the final solution with the rest of the class, and reflect on the problem-solving process in preparation for the next “run”</li>
    <li>Computers provide a great way of representing abstract knowledge in concrete form, and they also allow for the articulation of developing knowledge as well as sharing and combining of ideas with peers</li>
</ul>

<p>As the textbook definition at the very beginning mentioned, people working and researching in the learning sciences come from many different backgrounds, ranging from computer science all the way to design studies. But good ideas don’t just come from “learning experts” — I have seen an example of a <a href="https://www.colormephd.org/" target="_blank">brilliant educational coloring book developed by a chemical engineering researcher</a>! I’d say the field’s advances are based on the many unique insights that people bring with them, even if it’s just their own experiences with the schooling system. You can have a look at the <a href="https://www.isls.org/" target="_blank">International Society of Learning Sciences</a> in case you’re interested in looking into the field some more.</p>

<p>I said that this was the final note, but as you probably can tell, what this <em>actually</em> does is open up many more questions about the present and future of learning and teaching, not just in schools but also in informal settings. Even just the book I quoted at various points, the <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/cambridge-handbook-of-the-learning-sciences/2E4224681267E61DBCE9B27630ED17BA" target="_blank">Cambridge Handbook of Learning Sciences</a>, has 800 pages covering many more angles and recommendations.</p>

<p>As I myself learn more about learning (or even learning about learning about learning?), I will continue to cover some of it in writing, much in the spirit of <em>expressing one’s reflection process</em>. So until next time, and thanks for reading!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Personal" /><category term="LearningSciences" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Not too long ago, probably sometime around summer last year, I first came across the term “Learning Sciences”. In case you’re hearing about it for the very first time right now, what comes to mind for you? What do you envision the field to be about? Hold that thought!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quotes and Comments on Creativity, Teaching, and Lifelong Learning</title><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/quotes-and-comments-lifelong-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quotes and Comments on Creativity, Teaching, and Lifelong Learning" /><published>2021-02-02T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-02T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/quotes-and-comments-lifelong-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/quotes-and-comments-lifelong-learning/"><![CDATA[<p>To conclude the year 2020, I put together quotes from two of the books I very much enjoyed reading, complementing them with a few personal comments. Some of the topics that occupied me in particular during the past twelve months were (lifelong) learning, teaching, creativity, and education as a whole. This text ended up being somewhat long, but as each of the quotes pretty much speaks for itself, feel free to skip any part!</p>

<h2>Lifelong Kindergarten</h2>
<p>To start off with my most recent read, <em><a href="http://lifelongkindergarten.net/" target="_blank">Lifelong Kindergarten</a></em> is both <b>a book</b> written by MIT professor <a href="https://www.media.mit.edu/people/mres/overview/" target="_blank">Mitchel Resnick</a> as well as the name of his research group that makes part of the <a href="https://www.media.mit.edu/groups/lifelong-kindergarten/overview/" target="_blank">MIT Media Lab</a>. While Resnick’s group specializes in learning research as whole, it places emphasis on the use of media and technology in enhancing creative learning experiences. Judging from one of the pictures I found, it must be rather fun to be part of the <em>Lifelong Kindergarten</em>:</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/resnick-480.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/resnick-800.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/resnick-1400.webp" />
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/resnick.jpeg" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
Mitchel Resnick and… legos. Photo source: <a href="https://nlg-consulting.net/2013/04/30/mitchel-resnick-sowing-the-seeds-for-a-more-creative-society-grow-a-generation-llc/" target="_blank">nlg-consulting</a>.
</div>

<p>But I promised quotes! Here’s one from the first chapters:</p>

<blockquote>
With ploughs we can cultivate, with telescopes we can see, with engines we can travel, far beyond the limits of our unassisted bodies. <b>But tools do more than extend our bodies: they expand our minds. Technology facilitates ideas that might otherwise be inconceivable.</b>
</blockquote>

<p>The discussion around whether infinite growth — with technology playing its part — ultimately does more harm than good is an important one. However, on an individual level, the tools and scientific knowledge ranging from a simple hammer all the way to sophisticated computers certainly enhance our environment and daily lives. They make the pursuit of ideas easier and potentially further reaching, especially when thinking of modern technology such as the internet.</p>

<p>In regards to learning, you could also consider the process of creating new technology to be a learning experience in itself! And that’s exactly where creativity and creative learning come into play:</p>

<blockquote>
The <b>Creative Learning Spiral</b> is the engine of creative thinking. As kindergarten children go through the spiral, they develop and refine their abilities as creative thinkers. They learn to develop their own ideas, try them out, experiment with alternatives, get input from others, and generate new ideas based on their experiences. Unfortunately, after kindergarten, most schools shift away from the Creative Learning Spiral. Students spend much of their time sitting at desks, filling out worksheets, and listening to lectures — whether from a teacher in the classroom or a video on the computer. <b>Too often, schools focus on delivering instruction and information rather than supporting students in the creative learning process.</b>
</blockquote>

<p>The <em>Creative Learning Spiral</em>, another of Resnick’s concepts, encompasses the building blocks <em>imagine, create, play, share and reflect</em> (for an extensive description of what each entails, see the corresponding, very concise 6-page paper available <a href="https://web.media.mit.edu/~mres/papers/kindergarten-learning-approach.pdf" target="_blank">here</a>).</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/spiral-480.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/spiral-800.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/spiral-1400.webp" />
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/spiral.png" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
The Creative Learning Spiral. Source: <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/figure/The-spiral-of-creative-learning-The-kindergarten-approach-to-learning-Resnick_fig1_331310419" target="_blank">Mitchel Resnick (2007)</a>.
</div>

<p>What I want to pick up on here is the <em>one-way street of teaching</em> described in the quote above, which has become especially apparent to me lately, not least because of the global pandemic. In connection to the work of the <em>Lifelong Kindergarten</em> group, I would love to see things like <b><a href="https://scratch.mit.edu/" target="_blank">Scratch</a></b> used more often in schools and (online) classrooms. Looking at the research in the fields of educational and learning sciences (some of which is mentioned in my previous article, <a href="https://adaniabutto.medium.com/game-based-learning-and-21st-century-skills-c8763569d44e" target="_blank">Game-Based Learning And 21st Century Skills</a>), there really is only little if not no reason for many of the educational systems to hold on to their traditional ways of going about teaching and learning.</p>

<p>On a similar note, other approaches naturally come with their own challenges:</p>
<blockquote>
In her studies, Karen [<a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/kbrennan" target="_blank">Karen Brennan, Harvard University</a>] found that there are problems with both too much structure and too little structure. With too much structure, young people can’t work on what they want to work on. With too little structure, many aren’t able to come up with ideas or follow through on ideas. Karen rejects the idea that structure and agency should be seen in opposition to each other. She argues for the “best of both worlds,” proposing learning environments that “employ structure in a way that amplifies learner agency.”
</blockquote>

<p>Reflecting back on my own (ongoing) experience with self-assigned learning on platforms such as <a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/" target="_blank">Khan Academy</a> and <a href="https://ocw.mit.edu/" target="_blank">MIT OpenCourseWare</a>, it is relatively easy for a lack of structure to emerge in such environments. I imagine that with COVID, this has been one of the main challenges for many students throughout all stages of education, and might just continue to be so for the coming years. Resnick suggests and employs some interesting solutions in his book, such as <a href="https://theclubhousenetwork.org/" target="_blank">Computer Clubhouses</a>. While such an approach to STEM education might translate relatively well to an online setting, non-STEM subjects seem to present more of a challenge.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, many institutions and businesses are putting much thought and effort towards these issues (as solving them is also financially rewarding, as can be seen on the example of <em>Zoom</em>). If you’re interested in reading more on that, I have mentioned other promising examples of educational software and tools in an earlier text of mine, <em><a href="https://adaniabutto.medium.com/walking-a-tightrope-a-closer-look-at-microsoft-education-dc3bdfd9db92" target="_blank">Walking a Tightrope: A closer look at Microsoft Education</a></em>.</p>

<h2>“Surely You’re Joking, Mr. Feynman!”</h2>
<p>The second book I’d like to mention and comment on is <em>“Surely You’re Joking, Mr. Feynman!”</em>, where <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Feynman" target="_blank">Richard Feynman</a> describes some of his memories and other parts of his biography. The Nobel Prize-winning professor of Physics was well known for his engaging and ‘unusual’ way of teaching and explaining complex topic––part of his legacy are the highly praised <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Feynman_Lectures_on_Physics" target="_blank">Feynman Lectures on Physics</a></em> as well as the very popular <em><a href="https://www.colorado.edu/artssciences-advising/resource-library/life-skills/the-feynman-technique-in-academic-coaching" target="_blank">Feynman Technique</a></em>.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/feynman-480.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/feynman-800.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/feynman-1400.webp" />
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/feynman.png" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
Richard Feynman holding a lecture in 1959. Picture source: <a href="https://speakola.com/ideas/richard-feynman-nanotechnology-lecture-1959" target="_blank">Speakola</a>.
</div>

<blockquote>
… After the lecture, I talked to a student: “You take all those notes — what do you do with them?” “Oh, we study them,” he says. “We’ll have an exam.” “What will the exam be like?” “Very easy. I can tell you now one of the questions.” He looks at his notebook and says, “‘When are two bodies equivalent?’ And the answer is, ‘Two bodies are considered equivalent if equal torques will produce equal acceleration.’ ” <b>So, you see, they could pass the examinations, and “learn” all this stuff, and not know anything at all, except what they had memorized.</b>
</blockquote>

<p>Note that this particular interaction took place sometime around the early 1950s (!), when Feynman was on a sabbatical in Brazil teaching at the <em>Centro Brasileiro de Pesquisas Físicas</em>. But I believe that this way of learning is still very much present today, even all the way up in higher education. In fact––and this is not much of a controversial take, as far as I’m concerned––, the way exams are structured in many educational systems, rote learning is often <em>encouraged</em>. Thus, my personal takeaway is to even more so challenge my own ‘understanding’ in ways similar to what Feynman suggested. More importantly, this approach does not have to be exclusive to the school context, but may also include questions such as: Why are days ‘shorter’ during winter than summer? What does exponential growth mean in the context of a pandemic? It is surprising how good we can be at fooling ourselves into thinking that we <em>understand</em> such things, even at the most basic level!</p>

<p>And lastly, to end on the note of (not) fooling yourself:</p>
<blockquote>
<b>The first principle is that you must not fool yourself — and you are the easiest person to fool.</b> So you have to be very careful about that. After you’ve not fooled yourself, it’s easy not to fool other scientists. You just have to be honest in a conventional way after that. I would like to add something that’s not essential to the science, but something I kind of believe, which is that you should not fool the layman when you’re talking as a scientist.
</blockquote>

<p>Although not everyone is a scientist, many people go on to be an expert in some way or form. It can be very easy to settle for one specific perspective or line of argument once you feel you’ve put sufficient thought, studying, and/or research into something. But even if so, if not all the more, there is value in continuously challenging one’s own ‘understanding’, just like Feynman describes. It is also for this reason that I plan to keep doing these writings, occasionally coming back to topics I had already visited at an earlier point, and to hopefully keep discovering new insights by doing just that!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="HigherEducation" /><category term="LearningSciences" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[To conclude the year 2020, I put together quotes from two of the books I very much enjoyed reading, complementing them with a few personal comments. Some of the topics that occupied me in particular during the past twelve months were (lifelong) learning, teaching, creativity, and education as a whole. This text ended up being somewhat long, but as each of the quotes pretty much speaks for itself, feel free to skip any part!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">(International) Scholarships for Swiss Students: Opportunities and Resources</title><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/international-scholarships-for-swiss-students/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="(International) Scholarships for Swiss Students: Opportunities and Resources" /><published>2021-01-22T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-22T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/international-scholarships-for-swiss-students</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2021/international-scholarships-for-swiss-students/"><![CDATA[<p>In Switzerland, as far as I’m informed, scholarships are mostly considered something that is to be awarded to students in dire need of financial support. Merit-based scholarships seem to be rather unheard of, and so they are only rarely actively promoted (or perhaps just in specific circles). And yet, at the very latest as one enters university, I would argue scholarships become one of the most useful and desirable things all around, especially if you plan to go on exchange abroad.</p>

<p>Thus — mostly out of self-interest —, I took the time to research some of the most well-established merit-based scholarships attainable for Swiss students. I want to note that this text is mostly a byproduct of having written along in said research process. It is by no means an exhaustive list or complete guide, and if you’re interested in applying to scholarships yourself, you should definitely do your own research. Furthermore, since scholarships and grants for PhD students and post-docs are a tad different, the contents of this text may not be useful if you fall into said category. However, there is one thing that applies to anyone applying for a scholarship, no matter the career stage: There’s a tremendous amount of paperwork coming your way. Consider yourself warned!</p>

<h2>What scholarships are there?</h2>
<p>For students that are also Swiss citizens or residents, <a href="https://www.swissuniversities.ch/en/service/scholarships-for-study-abroad/government-scholarships/scholarship-offers" target="_blank">swissuniversities</a> provides a decent first overview of national and international scholarships awarded by various governments and government bodies. They list a total of 30+ countries that offer study abroad with official financial aid, ranging from Australia to China all the way to Russia and the USA.</p>

<p>But while there are scholarships and grants for pretty much any field of study and most domains of “talent”, there are many nuances to what each individual scholarship actually entails:</p>

<blockquote>
The type, duration and amount of a scholarship varies greatly from country to country. Scholarships are awarded for studies, research, specialisations, teaching, art or language courses; the duration can last from a few weeks to several years. Normally, a government scholarship covers the cost of living and studying in the host country. Some countries, however, only award partial scholarships; in such cases, the scholarship recipient is personally responsible for covering the remaining costs. (Quote from swissuniversities)
</blockquote>

<p>So, in certain cases, you may actually have to apply to multiple scholarships if you don’t have any funds of your own. Fortunately, it’s not only governments that offer financial support! There are also independent foundations such as the <a href="https://www.studienstiftung.ch/" target="_blank">Schweizer Studienstiftung</a>, even some heritage-based ones (e.g. the <a href="https://blatterstiftung.ch/" target="_blank">Charles E. Blatter Stiftung</a>). Interestingly enough, the independent kind quite often awards scholarships based on place of birth and/or residence or other very specific criteria, e.g. religious affiliation. You can find an official list of all acknowledged Swiss (study-related) foundations <a href="https://www.edi.admin.ch/edi/de/home/fachstellen/eidgenoessische-stiftungsaufsicht/stiftungsverzeichnis.exturl.html/aHR0cHM6Ly9lc3YuZGVpbW9zLmNoL0hvbWUvUmVzdWx0cw==.html?Keyword=studium&amp;TopicId=&amp;Lang=de" target="_blank">here</a> and other useful links <a href="https://www.swissuniversities.ch/services/stipendien-ausland/weitere-informationen/stiftungen/foerderung" target="_blank">here</a> or <a href="https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/latvia/de/home/dienstleistungen/stipendien.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h2>What does the application process look like, roughly?</h2>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/writing-480.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/writing-800.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/writing-1400.webp" />
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/writing.jpg" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>

<p>When applying to scholarships, especially international ones, there are generally the following steps:</p>
<ol>
    <li><b>You check whether you meet the eligibility criteria.</b> Those often include aspects like age, citizenship, (family) income, language proficiency, grade point average, amount of study semesters completed, amount of study semesters left to complete, and not currently receiving any other scholarships or financial support. As I mentioned right before, you may also have to live in a certain canton or city or have other affiliations. This information can always be found online.</li>
    <li><b>You send in your application with all the required documents.</b> In 99% of cases, this includes your <em>CV</em>, <em>Transcript of Records</em> (an overview of all your courses and grades), a <em>Personal Statement</em> (why you should be awarded the scholarship and what you intend to do with it), an <em>essay</em> of some sorts, <em>proof of meeting the eligibility criteria</em> (e.g., language diplomas, financial records), and sometimes also <em>a study and budget plan</em>, as well as multiple <em>Letters of Recommendation</em> (LoR). LoRs often have to be from professors or other people of “status”, and not only is getting multiple of them not easy, they should also be full of praise. Furthermore, you may have to get <a href="https://www.eda.admin.ch/countries/germany/de/home/dienstleistungen/beglaubigung.html" target="_blank">certified copies of your documents</a> if they’re required to be in English or any other language. Besides it being a lot of effort to collect all these documents, it most often also costs quite a bit of money.</li>
    <li><b>Your application gets reviewed and you are (maybe) invited to a personal interview.</b> The interview is usually held by the board of the respective foundation/scholarship or their representatives. As far as I understand, questions posed in these interviews revolve around your motivations, qualifications and plans. As I don’t have any personal experience with this, you can find a lot of information and tips on this on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=fulbright+interview" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.</li>
    <li>Provided you pass the interview, what follows is the <b>final confirmation</b> that you were accepted. But then comes <b>information meetings and more paperwork</b>. The responsible people tell you what your next steps should be, and you go on to prepare for whatever your destination is. You may even have to attend another interview at the VISA office or apply for a spot at your desired university, possibly taking more tests (e.g. the GRE for US universities).</li>
    <li><b>You’re done!</b> Well, at least for the time being. Many scholarships also demand that you’re actively and consistently engaged in the network and community, for example taking part in meetings and events and writing essays or giving talks on your experience. But if you’ve come this far, chances are that you don’t mind doing those :-)</li>
</ol>

<p>You’ll find the above steps in most if not all scholarship application processes, no matter if you’re applying for the Schweizer Studienstiftung or some international scholarship. But as I previously mentioned, do keep in mind that certain scholarships come with very unique requirements, which is why starting early and reading through things yourself is crucial!</p>

<p>Lastly, I’d like to touch on one special case:</p>

<h2>The Fulbright Scholarship</h2>
<p>Now that Donald Trump has left office, one can finally think about going to the USA again! And one of the best ways of doing so is through the <a href="" target="_blank">Fulbright scholarship</a>––a very prestigious accolade. It is specifically aimed at exchange in study and research between the US and other nations and does not fund anything other than that.</p>

<p>The relevant program for (pre-PhD) Swiss students is the <em>Fulbright Foreign Student Program</em>. You’ll find more extensive information on it and other options <a href="https://ch.usembassy.gov/education-culture/fulbright/" target="_blank">here</a>, but let me give you a quick summary:</p>

<p><b>Fulbright Foreign Student Program</b></p>
<blockquote>
If you want to pursue: a Master’s or Ph.D. degree; non-degree coursework; or Ph.D. research.

The Grants are four to ten months in length and not renewable. They are to be used toward the cost of tuition and other academic expenses. In general, a grant for one academic year is about $20,000.
</blockquote>

<p>A general heads-up: The Fulbright Scholarship application window has <em>one</em> deadline per year (sometime in August), and each application cycle is for the award of the scholarship in the <em>following</em> year. In other words, if you apply in summer of 2021, you’re effectively applying for the scholarship starting in autumn of 2022. Taking into account that you have to gather all of the required documents well before that, you should probably start planning <em>1.5 to two years in advance</em>. Fun, isn’t it?</p>

<p>One of the program’s downsides is that you only have little power over which university you’ll eventually go to (unless the universities approach you). <a href="https://www.swissuniversities.ch/service/stipendien-ausland/grants-for-the-usa/fulbright-student-grants" target="_blank">With the support of the Institute of International Education (IIE)</a>, you will apply to four or five US universities, going through the regular application process just like all the US students (AKA even more paperwork). As everyone knows, getting into some of the “better” schools in the US is extremely competitive. It is said that the prestige of the scholarship does help with your chances, though.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/mit-480.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/mit-800.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/mit-1400.webp" />
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/mit.jpg" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>

<p>I also wanted to cover a second special case, namely going on exchange for study and research in England. It is fascinating to me how institutions like Cambridge and Oxford basically defy the entire higher education system with some of their structures and systems. But I’ll leave that for next time and end with some final summarizing thoughts instead.</p>

<h2>What does one do with all that information?</h2>
<p>In conclusion, I would say that one of the biggest hurdles in applying to scholarships is the administrative side. You have to see how you get to the relevant information yourself (at least initially), you have to think far ahead, you need to be able to manage and keep track of many things, and you have to be ready to hand in piles of documents on a regular basis, all without a guarantee that it will pay off.</p>

<p>Now, of course this isn’t me criticizing the scholarships themselves––without them, many would not even be able to study let alone leave their country. As some of them award very large sums of money, there <em>should</em> be certain barriers and hurdles. This is just to say that you should keep all these points in mind when deciding to take on all that work.</p>

<p>On the upside, the process of applying for single exchange semesters, for example by support of SEMP (the Swiss equivalent of ERASMUS), is much more straightforward, although not to be underestimated either. I may cover that in a later text.</p>

<p>Once more, I recommend starting the process by going through the webpage of <a href="https://www.swissuniversities.ch/service/stipendien-ausland/regierungsstipendien" target="_blank">swissuniversities</a>. Besides that, YouTube and Google are your friend when looking for personal tips coming directly from scholarship recipients!</p>

<hr />

<p><em>I was fortunate enough to be selected as a principal candidate for the Fulbright Scholarship in September 2021. If you have any questions regarding the application or placement process, feel free to <a href="mailto:adaniabutto@gmail.com" target="_blank">shoot me an email</a>!</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="HigherEducation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In Switzerland, as far as I’m informed, scholarships are mostly considered something that is to be awarded to students in dire need of financial support. Merit-based scholarships seem to be rather unheard of, and so they are only rarely actively promoted (or perhaps just in specific circles). And yet, at the very latest as one enters university, I would argue scholarships become one of the most useful and desirable things all around, especially if you plan to go on exchange abroad.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Game-Based Learning and 21st Century Skills</title><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2020/gbl-and-21st-century-skills/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Game-Based Learning and 21st Century Skills" /><published>2020-10-12T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-12T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2020/gbl-and-21st-century-skills</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2020/gbl-and-21st-century-skills/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Game-Based Learning</em> (GBL) is one of those things that kind of sound too good to be true. How could it be that games teach us things in an effective manner? After all, most of the commonly known ones are designed for entertainment. Furthermore, digital games are often made so that the story takes place in a fictional world nothing like ours, take <em>Super Mario</em> for example. However, that’s not exactly what researchers mean when they speak of GBL. Let’s have a look at the definition(s) first.</p>

<h2>What exactly is Game-Based Learning (GBL)?</h2>
<p>So, what falls under GBL? According to <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2016.05.023" target="_blank">Qian and Clark (2016)</a>, the term is defined as <b>an environment where both the game content and game play induce skill and knowledge acquisition</b>. This means that the activities taking place as part of the game involve <b>problem solving as well as <b>challenges</b> that give the player some sense of achievement once completed. Now this is obviously a very broad definition.</b></p>

<p>If the first thing that came to your mind is something like the “ladders game” or card games, then you’re absolutely right—these do in fact also count. It’s just that the recent focus of GBL research has been set on <em>digital</em> game-based learning, although incorporating digital technologies is not a must per se. You can find some examples of GBL-oriented video games on <a href="https://education.mit.edu/project-type/games/" target="_blank">MIT’s Teacher Education Program website</a>.</p>

<p>Other terms that one might come across within the field are <em>Serious Games</em> (SG), <em>Gamification</em> or <em>Playful Learning</em>. There seems to be an ongoing discussion on how to define and separate those, but here are some basic outlines I found:</p>

<ul>
    <li><em>Gamification</em> encompasses extracting elements and structures from games and applying them to more “serious” environments like companies, schools or households</li>
    <li><em>Playful Learning</em> does not necessarily utilize games for learning, but rather emphasizes some of the playful components of learning</li>
    <li><em>Serious Games</em> are &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Serious_game target="_blank"&gt;“designed for purposes other than pure entertainment”&lt;/a&gt; and might for example help with the training of doctors. The term also includes simulations: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2017.10.040" target="_blank">Lamb et al. (2018)</a> mention that “Call of Duty, if used to train military personal in room clearing techniques, could be considered an example of a Serious Game”</li>
</ul>

<p>You could technically say that GBL is an umbrella term for all of the above, but not everybody in the research community seems to agree with that. For the sake of this story, we’ll go with this (simplified) definition though. Now let’s have a look at the research that has been done so far!</p>

<h2>What does the Research say about the Effectiveness of GBL?</h2>
<p>As with all other research that deals with such questions, there are no definitive answers — nevertheless, there are interesting findings that are worth discussing. In a recent meta-analysis by <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2016.05.023" target="_blank">Qian and Clark (2016)</a>, 29 relevant studies published between 2010 and 2014 were investigated. The authors focused on <b>GBL in relation to 21st century skills</b> (a wide range of skills including but not limited to critical thinking, creativity, collaboration, communication as well as media and technology skills), and provide us with the following takeaways:</p>
<ul>
    <li><b>While 21st century skills by themselves are only a small subfield of GBL research, most of the 29 papers focused on the development of critical thinking skills</b>. Only few investigated creativity and collaboration, and only one single study took a closer look at communication skills</li>
    <li><b>Participants covered a wide range of ages</b>, from K5 (5 to 11 years old) up to graduate level students, which is fantastic — in comparison, action video game research focuses almost entirely on young adults</li>
    <li><b><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/social-sciences/constructivism" target="_blank">Constructivism</a> was the learning theory that was most often referred to</b> by studies, however, across the field as a whole, many studies seem to fail to address learning theories in the theoretical foundation of their research (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compedu.2012.05.003" target="_blank">Wu et al., 2012</a>). This might have something to do with the outcomes of said research</li>
    <li><b>Fewer than half of the studies reported effect sizes</b>, although most (85%) reported significant effects. This is unfortunate as it limits the conclusions that can be drawn from their results</li>
    <li>The results of the studies that found significant effects seemed to mostly depend on game design, while <b>“game design elements proven successful in the entertainment game industry are most likely to lead to effective learning“</b>. Examples of such critical elements would be <em>Competition</em>, <em>Collaboration</em> and <em>Exploration &amp; Discovery</em>, which are very prevalent in non-educational video games</li>
    <li>In connection to that last point, <b>design-based games seemed to work best in improving 21st century skills</b>, despite them not having educational goals!</li>
</ul>

<h2>Conclusions and Outlook</h2>
<p>The authors of the cited meta-analysis state that <b>“a game-based learning approach might be effective in facilitating students’ 21st century skill development”</b>. One thing to keep in mind is that the investigated studies are already six to ten years old, and as all technological fields move very rapidly, reviews of more recent studies are needed!</p>

<p>While some improvements in 21st century skills can evidently be achieved via GBL (e.g. critical thinking), there’s still a lack of research when it comes to some other ones (e.g.communication and creativity). However, in the past, research on GBL has shown that educational games are positively linked to other learning outcomes such as cognitive ones (e.g. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.compedu.2012.03.004" target="_blank">Connolly et al., 2012</a>). Thus, <b>the domain as a whole seems promising and current challenges mostly lie in the effective design of the educational games</b>. This requires new approaches to avoid ending up with the same drill and narrow academic focus in the gameplay that can (sometimes) be found in the classroom.</p>

<p>I myself will have a closer look at some of the more successful educational games such as <a href="https://education.mit.edu/project/the-radix-endeavor/" target="_blank">MIT’s “The Radix Endeavor”</a> to try and figure out what sets it apart from others.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="LearningSciences" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Game-Based Learning (GBL) is one of those things that kind of sound too good to be true. How could it be that games teach us things in an effective manner? After all, most of the commonly known ones are designed for entertainment. Furthermore, digital games are often made so that the story takes place in a fictional world nothing like ours, take Super Mario for example. However, that’s not exactly what researchers mean when they speak of GBL. Let’s have a look at the definition(s) first.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Walking a Tightrope: A Closer Look at Microsoft Education</title><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2020/walking-a-tightrope-microsoft-edu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Walking a Tightrope: A Closer Look at Microsoft Education" /><published>2020-10-12T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-12T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2020/walking-a-tightrope-microsoft-edu</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2020/walking-a-tightrope-microsoft-edu/"><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve read my past two stories on <a href="https://medium.com/@adaniabutto/game-based-learning-and-21st-century-skills-c8763569d44e" target="_blank">Game-Based Learning</a> and <a href="https://medium.com/@adaniabutto/exciting-projects-at-the-intersection-of-video-games-computer-science-and-education-eaa5b2c19032" target="_blank">exciting projects at the intersection of video games, CS and education</a>, then you’ve probably noticed that I’ve been on the lookout for positive  examples of novel approaches to learning and teaching, especially those  involving digital technology.</p>

<p>Incidentally, I came across the docudrama <em><a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt11464826/" target="_blank">The Social Dilemma</a></em> yesterday, which  reminded me why it’s so important to have online platforms, products  and software that are designed in a way so that their use and content is  of benefit to the user. Now this doesn’t necessarily mean that the  creator can’t make profit or can’t use certain design techniques to  capture people’s attention more effectively, but it is a balancing act  that can quickly spiral out of control, which I thought <em>The Social Dilemma</em> illustrated quite well.</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/socialdilemma-480.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/socialdilemma-800.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/socialdilemma-1400.webp" />
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/socialdilemma.jpeg" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
Picture Source: <a href="https://livewire.thewire.in/out-and-about/why-the-social-dilemma-wont-make-me-quit-social-media/" target="_blank">LiveWire</a>
</div>

<p>So, are there any examples that seem like they’re successfully doing this  balancing act? Being a student myself, I have primarily been working  with <a href="https://zoom.us/" target="_blank">Zoom</a> and <a href="https://moodle.org/" target="_blank">Moodle</a>. The former is a tool used for online lectures as well as video/conference calls in general and has only recently come into play  for me, together with COVID. The latter is primarily used for  information exchange between educators and students (e.g. upload of  lecture slides or updates regarding exams/homework) and has been in use since the beginning of my studies.</p>

<p>As college and university students are expected to be well-organized and  autonomous for the most part (rightfully so), the  Zoom-and-Moodle-approach seems to be working well in most cases — it did  in mine. As far as I can tell, students as well as educators have  quickly adapted to blended and/or online learning, with the exception of  some initial difficulties when it came to figuring out all the  software/platform features (muting your microphone seems to be  especially complicated).</p>

<p>However, the needs and capabilities of people in higher education obviously differ from those of people in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primary_school#Levels_of_education" target="_blank">primary and secondary education</a>,  one simple example being that students at lower educational stages require much more guidance. This got me wondering, what solutions have  we come up with for that specific group? One of the go-to tool and resource providers seems to be <a href="https://education.microsoft.com/en-us" target="_blank">Microsoft Education</a>, which is why I want to take a closer look at that today.</p>

<h2>What does Microsoft Education entail?</h2>
<p>Entering Microsoft Education’s website, there’s a paragraph that says: “A  focused learning environment can be a challenge in hybrid learning. Microsoft Education is here to support multimedia experiences that keep  educators, students, and families connected.”</p>

<p>Looking through the navigation bar, there’s a wide range of options and offers, from training courses for educators (e.g., <a href="https://education.microsoft.com/en-us/resource/0c6e9c42" target="_blank">on special education and accessibility in remote learning</a>) to lesson plans for STEM (e.g., <a href="https://education.microsoft.com/en-us/hackingStem" target="_blank">project-based activities for remote learning</a>). I can’t speak on the exact content of these offers since I neither have  access to them nor am I an educator myself. Instead, I conducted a  quick search on empirical studies that pick up on Microsoft Education’s  effectiveness, but it came back with no results. Taking into  consideration that the COVID situation is still ongoing and such studies  sometimes take years until they’re published, this isn’t exactly  surprising.</p>

<p>Fortunately, Microsoft Education has a <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/education/stories" target="_blank">case study section</a> on their own webpage, from which I was able to gather some (qualitative) insights:</p>

<h2>Case studies and Feedback on Microsoft Education</h2>
<p>There  are dozens of case studies and reports available from schools all over  the world. Many of them include interesting stories, so if you’ve got  the time, <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/education/stories" target="_blank">you should go have a look for yourself</a>! Here’s a rough outline of the feedback from a few select institutions of primary, secondary as well as higher education:</p>
<ul>
    <li>Primary education institutions such as <a href="https://customers.microsoft.com/en-us/story/783715-omnimundo-education-windows10-office365-surface-belgium-en" target="_blank">Omnimundo from Belgium</a> mention how OneNote and other apps like <a href="https://www.lifeliqe.com/" target="_blank">Lifeliqe</a> help students stay engaged. A <a href="https://customers.microsoft.com/en-us/story/748341-ecole-elementaire-mont-tournier-edu-skype-en-france" target="_blank">primary school in France</a> mentions having used tools like <a href="https://education.skype.com/" target="_blank">Skype Mystère</a> (description below) with success.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
Skype  Mystére is a game that allows kids to learn about art, culture, the  environment and geography and sciences. The way it works is that a game  is played between two different classes, who strive to reach a simple,  common goal: each class must guess the geographical location of the  other by asking the class’ members questions. A good practice for this  game is to assign a specific role (whether the role be that of a  detective, thinker, cartographer, etc.) to each student. There is an  element in the game’s difficulty in that the questions asked must always  be closed, meaning that they can only be appropriately answered with  ‘yes’ or ‘no.’
</blockquote>
<ul>
    <li>One implementation that is especially remarkable to me is the usage of the <a href="https://education.minecraft.net/" target="_blank">Minecraft Education Edition</a> (game-based learning!) in 8 <a href="https://customers.microsoft.com/en-us/story/748348-thomas-pagotto-albacraft-minecraft-education-france-en" target="_blank">primary school classes in France</a> to digitally reproduce an archaeological site. The project got teachers as well as students very excited. Here’s the result:</li>
</ul>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/minecraft-480.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/minecraft-800.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/minecraft-1400.webp" />
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/minecraft.jpeg" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
A picture of the archaelogical site in Minecraft. Source: <a href="https://customers.microsoft.com/en-us/story/748348-thomas-pagotto-albacraft-minecraft-education-france-en" target="_blank">Microsoft Education</a>.
</div>

<ul>
    <li>Institutions of secondary education, e.g. singular ones in Hungary [<a href="https://customers.microsoft.com/en-us/story/760807-levay-jozsef-education-office365-hungary-en" target="_blank">1</a>] &amp; [<a href="https://customers.microsoft.com/en-us/story/761196-mozgasjavito-office365-education-hungary-en" target="_blank">2</a>], <a href="https://customers.microsoft.com/en-us/story/761379-colegio-vascodagama-education-teams-portugal-en" target="_blank">Portugal</a> and <a href="https://customers.microsoft.com/en-us/story/760050-galilee-education-win10-o365-en-france" target="_blank">France</a> that tested some of Microsoft Education’s products more extensively (sometimes in form of year-long fully digital classes) report having had mostly positive experiences. Some of them voice rather steep learning curves in getting to know all the features.</li>
    <li>The use of some tools in Higher Education, such as <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-gb/" target="_blank">Microsoft Azure</a> in research at <a href="https://customers.microsoft.com/en-us/story/792956-leiden-university-education-azure-netherlands-en" target="_blank">Leiden University</a> in the Netherlands and <em>Microsoft Teams</em> in teaching, e.g. at <a href="https://customers.microsoft.com/en-us/story/821344-imperial" target="_blank">Imperial College London</a>, UK, has resulted in positive feedback on usability and effectiveness</li>
</ul>

<p>I’ll  let you decide what to make of all that, considering that the case  studies were conducted by Microsoft Education themselves. A remaining  challenge seems to be the conduct of fair and effective online exams,  which the reports have not touched on. Other obvious issues would be  dependence on (stable) internet connection and financial barriers (what  if the parents can’t afford to buy the needed devices?). On the upside,  some of the schools state that they pay for the needed devices, at the  very least when it comes to using them in the classroom.</p>

<p>Overall,  I gained a positive first impression of Microsoft Education. I’m  looking forward to reading future (independent) quantitative studies,  possibly looking at educational outcomes, effects on motivation,  attention, creativity, problemsolving and other relevant aspects — the  list is long. I also hope to get to test some of the mentioned  applications and products myself, possibly by using them for my own  studying.</p>

<p>If you happen to have any thoughts on this matter, personal experience  with Microsoft Research or links to relevant research, let me know! That’s all for today — thanks for reading, and until you next time.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="LearningSciences" /><category term="Technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you’ve read my past two stories on Game-Based Learning and exciting projects at the intersection of video games, CS and education, then you’ve probably noticed that I’ve been on the lookout for positive examples of novel approaches to learning and teaching, especially those involving digital technology.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">World University Rankings: Are They of Any Use?</title><link href="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2020/world-university-rankings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="World University Rankings: Are They of Any Use?" /><published>2020-10-12T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-12T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2020/world-university-rankings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://github.com/pindi-krishna/pindi-krishna.github.io/writings/2020/world-university-rankings/"><![CDATA[<p>World University Rankings are an interesting phenomenon. Some of their first editions were published <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/College_and_university_rankings#Major_international_rankings" target="_blank">around the early 2000s</a>, and they seem to have become increasingly controversial over the years.</p>

<p>The rankings that are named to have the largest audiences and possibly also the largest impact would be the <a href="https://www.topuniversities.com/qs-world-university-rankings" target="_blank">QS World University Rankings</a>, the <a href="https://www.timeshighereducation.com/world-university-rankings/2021/world-ranking#!/page/0/length/25/sort_by/rank/sort_order/asc/cols/stats" target="_blank">Times Higher Education (THE) World University Rankings</a>, the <a href="http://www.shanghairanking.com/ARWU2020.html" target="_blank">Academic Ranking of World Universities</a> (ARWU) and the <a href="https://www.usnews.com/education/best-global-universities/rankings" target="_blank">US News &amp; World Report Global Ranking</a>.</p>

<p>I stumbled upon them about two years ago and did not really think much of it at first. At a later point, out of curiosity, I looked up the placements of universities that first came to my mind: Swiss universities in my surroundings, universities my friends have told me about, internationally reputable ones one reads about like Harvard, and so forth.</p>

<p>Some placements surprised me, for example how <a href="https://ethz.ch/en.html" target="_blank">ETH Zurich</a> was ranked as high as #6 in QS. Most of the other placements were in line with my expectations: Elite UK universities like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxbridge" target="_blank">Oxbridge</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivy_League" target="_blank">Ivy League institutions</a> filled the Top 20 in pretty much all of the tables. Naturally, I myself am also <a href="https://adaniabutto.medium.com/what-ive-learned-about-the-architecture-and-history-of-oxford-f3f39cefd128" target="_blank">guilty</a> of being fascinated with the reputation and history (and really mostly the architectural beauty) of institutions such as the University of Oxford.</p>

<p>All of this left me wondering: What can one really make of these rankings, and more importantly, <em>what are they based on</em>?</p>

<h2>The Data and the Methodology</h2>
<p>A first important question to answer might be how many universities there even are in the world. Turns out that finding this information is not exactly straightforward: Answers range from <a href="https://univ.cc/index.html" target="_blank">9696</a> to <a href="https://www.4icu.org/" target="_blank">13800</a> to <a href="https://www.whed.net/home.php" target="_blank">19800</a> to <a href="http://www.webometrics.info/en/distribution_by_country" target="_blank">30586</a> up to <a href="https://www.university-directory.eu/" target="_blank">51633</a>. Unfortunately, many of the sources behind these numbers don’t properly disclose how they arrived at their result. To make it short, the data from the <a href="https://www.whed.net/About.html" target="_blank">WHED</a> seems the most well-founded to me, so I’ll go with the number of <b>19800</b> for the sake of this next point.</p>

<p>Now, all of the mentioned rankings look at a pool of roughly 1500 to 2000 universities and eventually list a “Top 1000”, some going a bit further and listing a “Top 1500”. Realistically, what people really care about is the <b>“Top 100”</b> or <b>“Top 200”</b>, because who wants to scroll through a list of 1500 universities? Right, nobody. Either way, this raises a first big questionmark: How do you narrow down roughly 20’000 universities—among them some that were only recently founded (e.g. the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/University_of_Lucerne" target="_blank">University of Lucerne</a>, founded in 2000)— to the “best” 0.005% (Top 100) respectively 0.08% (Top 1500), not even giving the utmost majority a thorough look before deciding who makes the cut?</p>

<p>The most commonly used ranking indicators provide a first answer to this question. Here they are:</p>
<ul>
    <li>Number of publications</li>
    <li>Number of citations (e.g. within the past 5 years)</li>
    <li>Reputation in higher education and/or among employers (assessed via large surveys, sometimes including over 100'000 individuals)</li>
    <li>Faculty/student ratio</li>
    <li>Percentage of international students and faculty</li>
    <li>Income (focus varies; may be institutional, research or industry income, or all three)</li>
</ul>

<p>It is important to note that not all rankings include all of the listed indicators — some of them use unique ones that the others don’t use. The ARWU for example takes the number of alumni and staff winning Nobel Prizes/Fields Medals into account, while none of the others do so.</p>

<p>Furthermore, the amount of emphasis placed on each of the indicators also varies between rankings. If you’re interested in reading the details for each and every one of them, you’ll find all of the information available on the respective websites (e.g., THE has an <a href="https://www.timeshighereducation.com/sites/default/files/breaking_news_files/the_2021_world_university_rankings_methodology_24082020final.pdf" target="_blank">extensive PDF file</a> covering their methodology). The US News &amp; World Report provides a more or less compact overview that fits on a single screenshot:</p>

<div class="row mt-3">
    <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    <source media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/rankings-480.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/rankings-800.webp" />
    <source media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/rankings-1400.webp" />
    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" src="/assets/img/rankings.png" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
US News &amp; Global Report Ranking Indicators. <a href="https://www.usnews.com/education/best-global-universities/articles/methodology" target="_blank">Photo source</a>.
</div>

<h2>Criticism</h2>
<p>So far, not all of what I mentioned explicitly speaks <em>against</em> these rankings – there may be some variation in methodology, and the actual rankings do only include a fraction of the universities that are available worldwide, but isn’t that the entire point?</p>

<p>First of all, I do think it’s notable that these rankings are (relatively) transparent with their methodology, enabling the readers to decide for themselves what to make of the information available. <b>BUT</b>: How many high school graduates will bother to check up on the methodology if the ranking’s websites put out statements like “… Our flagship analysis, the THE World University Rankings, is the <em>definitive list</em> of the top universities globally”? Not too many, I would imagine.</p>

<p>Thus, as with most attempts to measure something that is inherently connected to personal opinions and biases, determining the quality of a university is hardly an objective process, and consequently these rankings should not be confused with and/or sold as facts. On the other hand, I would also not want to label them as <em>completely</em> useless or inaccurate — I simply think it has to be made clear that they need to be taken with a grain (or maybe rather a teacup) of salt.</p>

<p>I want to further include a few points that were brought up in a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-03312-2" target="_blank">news article by Elizabeth Gadd</a> published in <em>Nature World View</em> :</p>

<blockquote>
… [The rankings] favour publications in English, and institutions that did well in past rankings. So, older, wealthier organizations in Europe and North America consistently top the charts. …

… These league tables, produced by the Academic Ranking of World Universities (ARWU) and the Times Higher Education World University Ranking (THE WUR) and others, determine eligibility for scholarships and other income, and sway where scholars decide to work and study. Governments devise policies and divert funds to help institutions in their countries claw up these rankings. Researchers at many institutions, such as mine, miss out on opportunities owing to their placing. …
</blockquote>

<p>What I find interesting here is that you could probably name any one university that isn’t entirely falling apart to be “Top 200” or “Top 100”, and as more and more excellent students and faculty are drawn towards it due to its reputation, the number of outstanding achievements will continually increase, incoming funding and grants will increase over time, and so on — the label that originally might have been unfounded will most likely end up holding true.</p>

<p>I’m sure you yourself can think of many more points that could be brought up. However, instead of listing more criticisms, I would like to end this by mentioning some projects that attempt to give all of these rankings a positive spin.</p>

<h2>The Future (?)</h2>
<p>One might wonder whether there is a way to create a better version of these rankings, or if it would be better for them to be abolished for good. There are three organizations that pick up on this question (which were also linked in the Nature article):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.leidenranking.com/" target="_blank">The Leiden Ranking</a>: A ranking by Leiden University where “it is up to you to select the indicator that you wish to use to rank universities”. There are also a few interesting additions like the the <em>map view</em> which provides a geographical perspective. I have not yet had a thorough look at it, but if you’re interested in checking for yourself, the <a href="https://www.leidenranking.com/information/responsibleuse" target="_blank">ten principles for responsible use of university rankings</a> seem like a good start.</p>

<p><a href="https://inorms.net/about-us/" target="_blank">INORMS</a> and the <em>European Commission</em>: The International Network of Research Management Societies (INORMS) put together a working group to come up with <a href="https://inorms.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/what-makes-a-good-ranking-list-of-characteristics-version-2.pdf" target="_blank">criteria</a> for responsible conduct and use of university rankings. Furthermore, the European Commission very recently (September 2020) put out a publication named <em>Towards a 2030 vision on the future of universities in the field of R&amp;I in Europe</em> (a <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/publications/towards-2030-vision-future-universities-field-ri-europe_en" target="_blank">200-page document</a> — needless to say, I have not read much of it yet), which conducted case studies on some of the most popular university rankings, e.g. the THE ranking in chapter 4.4.4. If I do find anything of interest in there, I will make sure to bring it up in one of my next writings.</p>

<p>In conclusion, fortunately, a handful of (influential) organizations are now putting a good amount of resources into this matter. This only further underlines the importance. Naturally, universities are also facing many other challenges, not least because of the current situation — I suppose it will be interesting to see how it all fares out.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="HigherEducation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[World University Rankings are an interesting phenomenon. Some of their first editions were published around the early 2000s, and they seem to have become increasingly controversial over the years.]]></summary></entry></feed>